"Medically Assisted Death"
There are limits
to palliative care.
Even under hospice,
where one would assume
excellent palliative care,
there are those
who spend their last months
in uncontrolled pain.
And, this unbearable suffering,
despite our best efforts,
leads to requests by patients
to end their life prematurely.
Physician-assisted suicide,
or perhaps more accurately
physician-assisted dying
or medical aid in dying,
allows the terminally ill
to end their lives
through the voluntary
self-administration
of a lethal dose of medication
expressly prescribed
by a physician for that purpose.
U.S. public opinion has shifted
towards greater acceptance
of the process.
By 2017, fully two-thirds
of U.S. adults
support legalizing the practice,
though in the same year,
dozens of states reviewed
and rejected legalization.
A similar percentage
of terminally-ill patients
support it,
though only about one in nine
then seriously considered
requesting it for themselves.
Geriatrics physicians are split,
with 47 percent supporting
and 52 percent
opposing the practice.
Of 150 professional
medical societies,
not a single one
has come out in favor
of medical aid in dying.
Only 12 took
any sort of position,
mostly in opposition,
like the
American Medical Association,
though some, including
the American Academy of Hospice
and Palliative Medicine,
took an official
neutral position.
At the time I write this,
physician-assisted suicide
is only legal in nine states
plus the District of Columbia:
California,
Colorado,
Hawaii,
Maine,
Oregon,
Vermont,
and Washington,
plus New Jersey in 2019
and New Mexico in 2021.
After, or pending legalization,
most of the affected
state medical societies
adopted a neutral position.
Second only to Switzerland,
the first state
to legalize was Oregon,
with its Death With Dignity Act
passed
by ballot initiative in 1994
(though it didn't go into effect
until an injunction against it
was overturned in 1997).
It was upheld by the
U .S. Supreme Court in 2006,
after which other state bills
began to be introduced.
In the few decades
since it's been active,
about 3,000
terminally-ill Oregonians
have received
such prescriptions,
though only about 2,000
decided to go through with it.
(Nine patients regained
consciousness after ingestion.)
More recently,
that proportion has flipped,
with only about one-third
of those afforded the option
ended up using it
to end their lives,
supporting the premise that
much of the value to patients
may just lie
in having the choice.
In Oregon,
the Death With Dignity Act
now accounts for about
one in 200 deaths in Oregon,
similar to physician assisted
suicide rates
in some European countries
that have legalized it.
Medical aid
in dying is now legal
in Belgium, Luxembourg,
the Netherlands,
and Switzerland,
along with Canada, Colombia,
and one state
in Australia (Victoria).
In some countries,
that aid is more direct
than others.
In Belgium and the Netherlands,
euthanasia is legal,
where the physician can actively
administer the lethal medication
to someone seeking it
to end their life
due to unbearable,
incurable suffering.
Death by euthanasia
now accounts for about
one in 25 deaths
in those countries.
Euthanasia is illegal
everywhere in the United States.
In 40 states,
any physician aid in dying
is illegal
and punishable by law.
In Montana,
the state supreme court
effectively decriminalized it,
and a 2021 bill to remove it
as a defense against
charging prescribing doctors
with homicide
failed in the Montana Senate
with a vote of 25 to 25.
In contrast, V.S.E.D.
is legal throughout the U.S.:
voluntarily stopping
eating and drinking,
which I detail
in a series of videos
starting with
How to Die a Good Death.